The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Tayyib(طيب), we will begin In Sha Allah Ta'ala(إِنْ شَاءالله تعالى) with some events from the sixth year of Hijrah(هجرة),
before we move on to the story of Ibn-Al-Aqwa(اِبْنِ الْاَكْوَع).
This event is mentioned in Sahih Al-Bukhari(صحيح ألبخاري)
some men from the tribe of Uqul(عُقُل), and in one narration Urayna(عُرَيْنَةْ),
these narrations are in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم) and some other books of Hadith(حديث)
also mentioned in the books of Seerah(سيرة) by Ibn Is'haaq(إبن إسحاق) and Al-Waqadie(ألواقعدي).
Anyway so the narration is authentic.
These are men, some narrations say that, they're eight of them.
They were extremely poor suffering from malnutrition.
So, they came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and they came to Madina
they were from outside Madina, they were Bedouins.
They came to Madina and they accepted Islam and they were asking for Sadaqah(صدقه).
They became Muslim in Madina and they stayed with Ahlus-Suffah(إهل الصفه).
Ahlus-Suffah(إهل الصفه), I think we talked about them before in the initial stage of Madina.
Towards the back of Al-Masjid-Al-Nabawi(ألمسجد النبوي) there was a place that was shaded from the sun.
In which the homeless or poor of the Sahabah(صحابه) from the Muhajireen(مهاجرين), who have nowhere to stay.
They would stay in that place and the Ansaar(انصار) would bring food to them, or would invite them.
So, you would have one Ansaari(أنصاري) take one of them with him
some of them would take two,
then you have people like Saad Bin Ubadah(سعدبن عبادة) they would take 10,
they would take 10 men from Ahlus-Suffah(إهل الصفه) and would invite them.
Anyway so these eight men they became Muslim and they stayed with Ahlus-Suffah(إهل الصفه).
فَاسْتَوْخَمُوا الْمَدِيْنَهْ
They were feeling unhealthy
and this is something well known about Madina at that time, the climate of Madina was unhealthy.
In one narration, Ayesha رضي الله عنها said;
When they first made Hijrah(هجرة) to Madina that they suffered bouts of fever
and she said, that this area called Bat'haan(بطحان), it was full of stagnant water.
So, Allah-Ho-Alam(الله اعلم) is this a Malaria related fever or is it Typhoid, what exactly is it?
Is it a bacterial infections, viral infections? Allah-Ho-Alam(الله اعلم)
but diseases were endemic to Madina.
And these eight men, who came to Madina,
by the way, we also talked about for example some lines of poetry from Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) and Bilal(بلال)
when they came to Madina, they all became extremely ill with a very strong fevers.
Well, anyway these eight men who came into Madina,
they didn't like the climate, it wasn't befitting of their constitution,
so they asked Rasool Allah ﷺ and then said that,
اِنَّا اُنَاس الزَرْعَ
وَلَمْ نَكُنْ اَهل الْرِيْفْ وَاستوْخَمْنَا الْمَدِيْنَةْ
They said: We are people, who are shepherds
and we are not people, urban people, Ahl Ar-Reif(أهل ألريف), or people who are settled
and Madina is unhealthy for us.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
Well then I will give you permission to go out with my shepherd outside of Madina
and I order you to drink, from the milk and urine, of the camels of Sadaqah(صدقه).
So they went out and they started drinking from the milk of the camels
and the urine of these camels until they became healthy.
And it says, in one narration;
فَعَدَتَ اِلَيْهِمْ اَلْوَنُهُمْ
So, their natural color came back to them.
Because this is might be one indication that they were suffering from jaundice
or some liver disease which caused their colors to change, Allah-Ho-Alam(الله اعلم).
And now, after drinking the milk and urine of these camels, they became healthy again.
Well after becoming healthy, they were ungrateful, what they did is
They killed the shepherd of Rasool Allah ﷺ and they stole the camels
and they became Murtadd(مرتد), they have given up Islam and they fled.
This was in return to the generosity of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
The news reached to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
فَاَرْسَلَ فِي طَّلَبِهِمْ فَلَمْ تَرتفعِ الشَّمْسْ حَتَّى اَتَى بِهِمْ
The news reach to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and by the time the sun was rising, they were already brought back.
And it says that Rasool Allah ﷺ made a Dua(دُعَا) against them.
اَللَّهُمَّ عَمِّ عَلَيْهِمْ الطَّرِيْقْ وَجَعَلْهَا عَلَيْهِمْ اَضِّيق مِنْ مِّسْكِ جَمَلْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ made a Dua(دُعَا) against them, to blind them, and to make their paths narrow.
So, they became lost and they were brought back
and in one narration from Seerah(سيرة) it says, that when the news reach to Rasool Allah ﷺ
He was sitting with 20 young men from Al-Ansaar(ألأنصار)
and these are the ones, whom Rasool Allah ﷺ dispatched, to bring back these robbers.
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ do? How did he treat them?
It says in this narration, by Bukhari(بخاريْ),
فَاَمَرَبِمَسَامِيْرَ، وَاُحْمِيَّتْ فَكَوَاهُمْ بِهَا
He ordered that, their eyes be branded by hot iron nails,
وَقَطَّعَ اَيْدِيَهُمْ وَاَرْجُلَهُمْ
And he severed their arms, and their legs,
وَاَلْقَاهُمْ فِيْ الّحَرَّةِ يَسْتَسْقُوْنَ فلَا يُسْقَوْنْ
And he left them in a Al-Harr'ra(ألحره),
Al-Harr'ra(ألحره) is an area next to my Madina volcanic, tracks, covered with black volcanic rocks.
This is Al-Harr'ra(ألحره) it's right next to Madina,
they were left there and they would ask for water to drink
and they would not be provided with it.
حَتَّى مَاتُوا وَلَمْ يَحْسِمهُمْ
Until they died,
وَلَمْ يَحْسِمَهُمْ,
Al-Hasm(اَلْحسم) when, the limb is severed
they would use boiling oil to stop the flow of blood to stop the bleeding.
In their case, this was not done to them, so they bled till death.
Three points to make on this Hadith(حديث).
Number one, using urine, is urine Najs(نجس) or Tahir(طاهر)?
So what's the Fiqh(فقه) of it, without going into much detail
one could refer to the books of Fiqh(فقه) for this.
Some scholars based on this Hadith(حديث),
they Hukm(حكم) that the urine and dung of edible animals is Tahir(طاهر)
and these are Malik(مالك) and Ahmad(أحمد).
Imam Ahmad(اِمَامْ اَحْمَدْ) and Imam Malik(اِمِام مَالِك), this is their opinion.
While the rest of the Ulema(علماء) see that it is Najs(نجس).
Number two, using urine, as a cure as a medicine.
This has been a controversial issue,
and the non believers have used this, as a gate in which they would attack Hadith(حديث) through.
And also the ones who reject Hadith(حديث) and try to discredit Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم).
They also use this Hadith(حديث) as, an attacking point against the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and the disbelievers made the big deal about this issue of using urine as a medicine.
Now, I don't want to go into a lot of details regarding this point.
But just briefly because it's outside the context of Seerah(سيرة) just briefly, I would like to say that
urine has been used as medicine in many cultures around the world.
And even in modern medicine, it is used as an ingredient in some drugs
for example, there's a drug called Premarin
and this is the commercial name for a compound drug consisting primarily of conjugated estrogens.
I mean, this quote I'm reading it from Wikipedia,
isolated from mares urine, it is manufactured by YES pharmaceuticals
and has been marketed since 1942.
So, from 1942 until now, until today
this drug is widely prescribed, and it's still used.
And it says, Premarin has been one of the most widely used drugs in the United States.
So, if there are medicational benefits in a particular ingredient in urine
then modern medicine does not see any problem in using it
but because it is mentioned in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم) and attributed to Muhammadﷺ it's a big deal.
Without testing the validity of the prescription,
without looking into whether it is beneficial or not
they are attacking with preconceived notions.
Now, as a Muslim we should believe in it
as long as the Sanad(سند) of it is authentic and that's the case.
I mean we don't have to test it pharmaceutically and to prove the benefit of it
as long as Rasool Allah ﷺ said so... We believe it, that's the position of the Muslims.
But what the non Muslims, they should have put this to trial and experimented with it
before attacking the Muslims for it.
And there are some research papers that were done
on the anti viral qualities of camel urine
and the fact that it might have on the liver
and one can refer back to these research papers for more details.
The thing is that, it says in the Hadith(حديث), that they were cured from the disease that they had.
And one can use the different narrations, I mean, someone with medical background
can use the different narrations to try to find, leads to what particular disease these people sufferred from.
I recall that in one narration, I think it's in Muslim(مسلم)
it says that they suffered from a digestive disease.
But in another one, it says that their colors changed.
So, it could be jaundice something or it could be hepatitis or some problem with the liver.
Anyway, one can compile all of the different narrations and try to find out what the disease is
and then make an experiment on the different ingredients of camel urine,
to see how, it healed them from that particular disease that, they suffered from.
The third point is the extreme punishment that these men were subjected to.
Brothers and Sisters,
we never find in the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ before this event, or after this event
any punishment similar to the punishment that these men were subjected to.
So, the question is why?
why was this particularly severe punishment prescribed by Rasool Allah ﷺ.?
And also, this is a point that, the disbelievers use against Muhammadﷺ
to try to prove, so called violence that is in the Sunnah(سنة) in Islam.
Well as I mentioned, we never find anything similar to it, before or after.
This is the only time, in which we find such a severe punishment occurring
Abu Qalabah(أبوقلابة) one of the narrators of the Hadith(حديث), which is Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري)
he said, after mentioning the Hadith(حديث), he said;
فَهولآءِ قَتَلُوا وَسَرَقُوْا وَكَفَرُوْا بَعْدَ اِيْمَانِهِمْ وَحَارَبُوا الله وَرَسُوْلَه
He says; These men, they murdered and they stole, and they disbelieved, after believing
and they fought against Allah and His Messenger.
So, all of these crimes, combined, justified that punishment,
because all of these are severe crimes, murder, and then you have stealing
and then you have Riddah(ردة) and then we have Hirabah(حرابة)
which is armed robbery, and this carries a very severe punishment
which is mentioned, in Qur'an that one arm should be cut off and one foot should be cut off.
And in Hadith(حديث), Al-Muslim(اَلْمُسلم)
he says that, the reason why their eyes were branded,
is because they branded the eyes of the shepherd of Rasool Allah ﷺ, Yasa'ar(يَسار).
So, in Muslim(مسلم) it says that, the reason why their eyes were branded is
because they branded the eyes of the shepherd.
So, they were treated Bil-Misl(بالمثل), they were treated equally, Qisaas(قصاص), retribution.
Also Ibn Hajar(إبن حجر) comments that some of the Ulema(علماء),
some of the Ulema(علماء) see that this Hukum(حكم), this punishment is abrogated, Mansookh(منسوخ).
Qatadah(قتادة) says;
بَلَغَنَا اَنَّ رَسُوْل الله صلى الله عليه وسلم كَانَ اِذَ خَطَبَ بَعْدَ ذَالِكْ اَمَرَ بِصَدَقَة وَنَهَى عنِ الْمُثْلَهْ
Qatadah(قتادة) used to say we were told that Rasool Allah ﷺ after that
if he gives a Khut'ba(خطبة), he would encourage people to give Sadaqah(صدقه)
and he would prohibit them, from mutilation, from maiming
but this is not an agreed upon opinion, it's one opinion that this has been abrogated
some of the Ulema(علماء) say that it's not abrogated
but Rasool Allah ﷺ treated them that way as Bil-Misl(بالمثل) equally as they have treated the shepherd of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and we know that in Islam, if 100 people gathered together, to kill one person
then all of them are subjected to the Qisaas(قصاص), the retribution.
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) says;
If the residents of San'a(صنعاء) come together to kill one man
then all of them will be executed for that
this is the Hukm(حكم) of Sharia(شريعة) in Hudood(حدود).
So, these are some comments on this Hadith(حديث) in Bukhari(بخاري),
and as Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) mentioned, it occurred within the period of the sixth year of Hijrah(هجرة).
Some other events that occurred during that year,
these are small Saraya(سرلية), dispatches.
In Rabiul Awwal(ربيع اول) of that year Rasool Allah ﷺ sent or Ukkasha Bin Mahsan(عكاشة بن محصن)
with a force of 40 men to Ghamar Marzooq(غَمَرمَرْزُوْق)
the enemy fled from him and he encamped at their wells.
He then sent some men in pursuit of them and took 200 of their camels which, he led to Madina.
These were taken as Ghaneemah(غنيمه).
Also that year, was the dispatch of Abu Obaidah(أبوعبيدة) to Zul-Qissah(ذوالقصه)
he had with him 40 men, he made for them on foot
reaching them in the morning, while it was still dark.
They fled from him into the mountain heights
he captured one of their men and brought into the Messenger of Allah.
And then there was the dispatch of Muhammad Ibn Maslamah(محمدإبن مسلمه) with the force of 10 men,
the enemy hide from him until night
and then all of the men of Muhammad Ibn Maslamah(محمدإبن مسلمه) were killed
except he escaped but he was wounded.
Al-Yamdo'al(أليمدولِم), One day you win the next day you lose
that's the Sunnah(سنة) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
So, one cannot stop, the struggle just because of suffering a setback.
Muhammad Ibn Maslamah(محمدإبن مسلمه) was the only one from this group who escaped alive.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Zaid Bin Harissa(زيدبن حارثة) to Al-Jamoom(ألجموم)
he also sent Zaid Bin Harissa(زيدبن حارثه) to Bannu Thalabah(بنو ثعلبة).
He sends Zaid Bin Harissa(زيدبن حارثه) to Al-Ees(ألعيص).
Here we see Zaid Bin Harissa رضي الله عنه sent to lead three Sarayah(سرايه) within one year
and this shows us the level of the trust that Rasool Allah ﷺ has in Zaid Bin Harissa(زيدبن حارثه)
who was his former slave and Rasool Allah ﷺ, freed him
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ married him, to a woman
that the belongs the nobility of Makkah, Zainab Bint Jahash رضي الله عنها
we talked about her story.
And this shows us again the trust that Rasool Allah ﷺ had, in Zaid Bin Harissa(زيدبن حارثه)
a man who without Islam would never imagine in his life that he would lead an army,
he wouldn't even imagine that he would be a free man honored in the society,
let alone, lead an army that had some of the great men of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) or Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج) or Al-Aos(ألأوس).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ would appoint him, sometime later as, we will talk about to lead,
in one of the great battles of Islamic history Ghazwa Mo'ta(غزوة مؤته).
Only to be honored by Allahعَزّوجَلّ and die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) to Banni Saeed Bin Bakr(بني سعيد بن بكر) and they were sent,
because Rasool Allah ﷺ heard that, these people were planning on giving the Jews of Al-Khaybar(الخيبر) some assistance.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to prevent that.
And he sent Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) to them they did not fight,
they fled from Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) he captured one of their men,
and this man admitted to being a spy for them and they retrieve some information from him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ, you can see from the story
that he was very aware of what was happening around him
he had very strong intelligence of everything that was going on, in Arabia.
He had for example Khuza'a(خزاعه), acting as intelligence officers for him
getting information from Quraish(قريش)
he had information from the areas in which the Jews were living,
he had intelligence coming to him for what was happening in Ghatafaan(غطافان),
Rasool Allah ﷺ was not taken by surprise, in fact, he would take his enemies by surprise.
Rasool Allah ﷺ we can see that, not only were the Muslim strong in the battlefield
but they were very strong in reconnaissance, and gathering information.
Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه was sent to Doma-Tul-Jandal(دومة الجندل).
And the instructions were to go and give them Da'wah(دعوة) to Islam, if they accept Islam
then offer to marry the daughter of their king.
And that did happen and Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf(عبدالرحمن ابن عوف) married the daughter of their king Al-Asbigh Al-Kalbi(اَلْاَصْبَغْ اَلْكَلْبِيْ).
Her name was Tumadhir(تُمَاضِر) and she was married to Abdur Rahman Ibn Auf رضي الله عنه.
These are some scattered events that occurred in the six year of Hijrah(هجرة).
We move on to the seven year, now Rasool Allah ﷺ came back from Al-Hudaybiyya(اَلْحُدَيْبِيَة)
Musa Bin Uqba(موسى بن عقبه)
and by the way, Musa Bin Uqba(موسى بن عُقْبَه) is an author of Seerah(سيرة)
and the scholars say that his narrations are among the best
when it comes to the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
However, the book that he authored does not exist with us today.
What exists with us today are narrations from him by other scholars.
So, other scholars like a Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) like Al-Waqidie(ألواقعدي) they would narrate from Musa Bin Uqba(موسى بن عُقْبَه).
Musa Bin Uqba(موسى بن عُقْبَه) says that,
20 days after the arrival of Rasool Allah ﷺ to Madina from Al-Hudaybiyya(اَلْحُدَيْبِيَّة), he set out to Khaybar(خيبر).
Now Al-Hudaybiyya(اَلْحُدَيْبِيَّة) was a truce, between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
and the agreement was that, they would stop fighting for 10 years.
Now, rather than the Muslims taking rest from a very difficult five years
of continuous fighting with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and the allies of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
No, they did not take rest,
only 20 days after the arrival in Madina Rasool Allah ﷺ is marching out to Khaybar(خيبر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ has now, a peace agreement with Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
but there's the big problem of Al-Yahood(إليهود)
who were continuously conspiring against the Muslims.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ saw this as the appropriate moment
to once and for all stop the Yahood(إليهود) from their conspiracies against the Muslims.
And the only remaining stronghold of Al-Yahood(إليهود).
There is still another community of Yahood(إليهود) in Tayma(تيماء)
but this was the only remaining stronghold of Al-Yahood(إليهود)  and this was Khaybar(خيبر).
In fact it was the strongest area of Al-Yahood(إليهود) in the Arabian Peninsula.
On the way Amir Bin Aqwa رضي الله عنه was asked to make Nasheed(نشيد) for them,
the Bedouin way of singing poetry and this is Huda'a(هداء).
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) this had an effect on the camels,
the camels would become active and faster and stronger in their march if they become tired,
when they hear these Anasheed(اَنَاشِيْد).
So, Aamir(عامر) was told to make this Nasheed(نشيد) and he said;
Allah humma(اَللَّهُمَّ) without you we would not have been rightly guided***
Nor would we have given alms nor prayed***
We beseech you, to forgive what, we have done wrong***
May we be sacrificed for you***
We beseech you to send down, your serenity upon us***
To make our feet secure, when we meet our enemies***
And if they cry out trying to subvert us***
We will refuse already have the loudly sought others, help against us***
When Rasool Allah ﷺ heard these wonderful words from Amir Bin Aqwa(عامربن اكوع)
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yarhamo Hullah(يرحمهُ الله), may Allah have mercy on him.
And the Sahabah(صحابه) knew that when Rasool Allah ﷺ singles out an individual for mercy
that means, he will die as Shaheed(شهيد),
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) that's the understanding they had
as if Shahadah(شهادة) and mercy are related.
So when Rasool Allah ﷺ would say Yarhamo Hullah(يرحمهُ الله) may Allah have mercy on him.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ make that Dua(دعا)
the manifestation of this Dua(دُعَا)
would come in the form of Shahadah(شهادة) in the form of martyrdom.
So Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said;
وَجَبَتْ يا رسول الله,
It has become inevitable.
لَوْلَا مَتعتنا بِه
I wish you have allowed us to enjoy his company longer,
so they're not protesting that Aamir(عامر) would become a shaheed(شهيد).
They're happy for him that he would receive this blessing from Allahعَزّوجَلّ
but they just wanted to enjoy him longer because, they enjoy his company
and they would have desired that, they would have spent more time with him.
The Muslims reached to Khaybar(خيبر), the Yahood(يهود) of Khaybar(خيبر) as we said;
Rasool Allah ﷺ has taken his enemies by surprise,
they set out in the morning to go out of their fortresses into their farms,
so they came out with their equipment farming equipment, ready for work
and they suddenly see, the army in the horizon.
They run back into their fortresses saying;
محمد وَالْخَمِيْسْ، محمد وَالْخَمِيْسْ، محمد وَالْخَمِيْسْ،
Muhammad Wal Khamees(محمد والخميس) Al-Khamees(الخميس) means, the army, Muhammad(محمد) and the army,
Muhammad(محمد) and the army, Muhammad(محمد) and the army, these were their words
when they're fleeing and running away from Muhammadﷺ.
Now, these Yahood(يهود) they used to brag,
the Yahood(يهود) of Khaybar(خيبر), they used to brag and say that fighting us, is not like fighting the rest of the Arabs and
they were proud and happy and content with their fortresses and their, strong training
and the famous fighting men among them, such as Marhab(مرحب), and others.
But when they saw, the army of Muhammadﷺ, they fled and ran away
and this is because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
نُصِرْتُ بِرُّعْبَ مسيْرَةْ الشَّهْرْ
I was given victory through fear,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ puts fear in the hearts of the enemies of Muhammadﷺ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ laid siege to the fortresses of Khaybar(خيبر)
we're not talking about one fortress but many fortresses scattered around on hill tops and mountains, very well protected area.
The news spread and the Arabs knew very well, the strength of the location,
and strength of Al-Yahood(إليهود) in that area.
And Huwaitib Ibn Abdul Izzah(حويطب إبن عبدالعزة) who was one of the members of the envoys
who met with Rasool Allah ﷺ in Hudaybiyya(حُدَيْبِية).
When he went back to Makkah, he said;
He's narrating this, he said: When I left from Al-Hudaybiyya(الْحُدَيْبِيَة),
I knew that Muhammad(محمد) and his followers would be victorious.
This is the impression of the people,
people when they would come and meet with Rasool Allah ﷺ and see him, and hear him
and they would see, the conduct of the Muslims,
they would carry a certain impression, as we see with Urwa Bin Masood(عُرْوَة بن مسعود),
the impression, he had is that the way, Rasool Allah ﷺ is treated by his followers
is like no other in the world, it is unique
and he also came back with the impression that his followers are never going to give them up, no matter what happens.
Huwaitib Ibn Abdul Uzzah(حويطب إبن عبدالعزة), he came back with the impression that
these people are going to definitely win.
So, he and some other men from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) had a bet.
Some of them people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) like the Safwan Ibn Umayyah(صفوان ابن اُمَيَّة) they were for Al-Yahood(إليهود),
they said that Yahood(إليهود) will win
because of the reputation that they had.
While Huwaitib(حويطب) said Muhammadﷺ will win and the wager was 100 camels
that was the bet, a hundred camels.
So, the news has spread and it has gained the interest of people all over
to the extent that they would have a bet about it, in Makkah.
During the siege of one of the fortresses,
one of the fighters of Al-Yahood(إليهود), I think it's Marhab(مَرْحَب) he came out asking for a duel challenging the Muslims.
So, Aamir Ibn Al Aqwa(عامر ابن الاكوع) is the one who came out to meet him.
They exchanged a few blows with their swords
and then Marhab(مَرْحَب), he struck Aamir(عامر) with his sword
but the sword got stuck in the shield that, Aamir(عامر) had, it was leather or wood,
so it withheld his sword in it, and Marhab(مَرْحَب) was unable to pull it out.
So Aamir(عامر) took this as an opportunity to strike at Marhab(مَرْحَب) and kill him
but, his sword was short, so it came back on him and it struck, the upper part of his knee
and it hit an artery or vein and Aamir(عامر) bled to death and he died.
So now some people started saying that Aamir(عامر) has lost all of his deeds
because he has committed suicide.
Salamah(سلمة), who is his nephew, was very upset with that,
and depressed with what people were saying
and Rasool Allah ﷺ saw that on his face, so he asked him; What's wrong with you?
He said;
People are claiming that my uncle Aamir(عامر).
بَطُلَ عَمَلُه
That he lost all of his deeds.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Kadhaboo(كذبو), whoever said that, lied.
He will receive a double reward and then he raised, both of his fingers to signify double the reward.
He was a Mujahid(مجاهد), who struggled his best, and a few Arabs have matched him,
اِنَّه’ جَاهِدٌ مُجَاهِدْ قَلَّمَا مَشى عَرَبِيٌّ مِثْلُ
So, this is a badge of honor that, Amir Bin Aqwa رضي الله عنه received from Rasool Allah ﷺ
and what we just talked about earlier, the Dua(دُعَا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ happened.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yahamo Hullah(يرحمه الله)
the Dua(دُعَا) was accepted then it was accepted very soon.
He was killed in the same battle, Ghazwat-Khaybar(غزوة الخيبر).
There was a particular fortress that was giving the Muslims hard time
one after another Rasool Allah ﷺ would appoint leaders to open it and they would all failed.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ, one evening said;
لَاُعطيَّنَّ الرَاية غَدًا رَجُلًا يَفْتَحُ الله َعَلَى يَدَيْهِ يُحِبُ اللهَ وَرَسُوْلَه، وَيُحِبُّهُ اللهُ وَرَسُوْلَهْ
Tomorrow, I will give the banner to a man, whom Allah will open for him.
He loves Allah and His messenger, and Allah and His Messenger love him.
What a wonderful honor, Allah will open this fortress for him,
he loves Allah and His messenger and Allah and His Messenger love him.
Sahal Ibn Sa'ad(سهل إبن سعد) said;
فَلَمَّا اَصْبَحَ النَّاسْ غَدَّوْا عَلَى النَّبِيْ كُلَّهُمْ يَرْجُوْ اَنْ يُعْطَاهَا
Next day, in the morning all of the Sahabah(صحابه) went to Rasool Allah ﷺ
showing themselves, in front of him, to turns his attention towards them
because everyone of them, wanted that honor, for himself.
And this is in Al-Bukhari(إلبخاري).
And I want you, to pay attention to this statement, by Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب)
it's a striking statement. He said;
فَمَا اَحْبَبْتُ الْاِمَارَة قَطْ اِلَّا يَوْمَئِذٍ
And this is in Al-Muslim(المسلم).
He said: I never loved position of authority ever, except on that day
loving, to be an Ameer(اَمِيْر), loving to be in a position of authority, is something that everyone has
the love of being famous, the love of being known, the love of being an authority the love of being in power,
this is something natural to humans.
However, in Islam,
we are not supposed to seek for positions of authority to be dominant over others to give orders.
That is something that is discouraged,
when Al-Abbas(العباس) came to Rasool Allah ﷺ, asking him being the uncle of Rasool Ullah
asking him to appoint him in a position of authority, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اِنَّ لَا نُعْطِعْي هَذَالْاَمْرَ اَحَدًا سَئلَهُ اَو حَرَص عَلَيْهْ
We do not give this, to somebody who asks for it, or somebody who's eager to have it.
This is the Tarbiyyah(تربيعة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, this is the Tarbiyyah(تربيعة) of Islam.
And it reached to the level that Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) doesn't even desire it.
So, it's not like he's suppressing his desire for it, he doesn't want it
he has reached to the level, where he was able to force himself into not even wanting it
and it moved on, from that level of suppressing this desire into the level of genuinely not seeking it, and not loving it,
except that day, he wanted it, why?
Because of the honor and the promise of most of Rasool Allah ﷺ that
this is a man that loves Allah, and His Messenger and Allah and His Messenger love him.
This is something that every Sahabi(صحابي) wanted to have.
So, brothers and sisters, this is an opportunity for us to remind ourselves
on this danger of Hubb-Al-Ammarah(حب الأمارة) of Love of leadership.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says, in a Hadith(حديث) narrated by Tirmizi(تِرْمِذِي) and it is Hasan Sahih(حسن صحيح).
مَا ذئْبَانِ جَائعان اُرْسِلَا فِيْ غَنَمْ بِاَفْسَدَلَهَا مِنْ حرص المرء عَلَى الْمَالِ والَشَّرفْ لِدِيْنِه
If you sent two hungry wolves, on some sheep they will not corrupt the sheep more than,
the eagerness that the person has for wealth and position of authority, for his religion.
So, the meaning of this Hadith(حديث) is, that if a person has the love and eagerness to have money,
and to have authority, these two things are dangerous on his religion,
just like the danger of sending two hungry wolves on sheep.
Now, if you sent to hungry wolves and sheep, what could they do?
They would ruin them.
And the same thing, would happen to your religion
if you allow the love of money and the love of authority to take over.
So, these are two things, that we have to make Mujahidah(مجاهده) against we have to struggle against.
And it's a continuous struggle
it's not something that you do for a while and then you Leave
it's a continuous struggle that we have with our Nafs(نفس),
and in Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري).
اِنَّكُمْ سَتَحْرِصُوْنَ عَلَى الْاِمَارَةَ وَ اِنَّهَا ندَامَة يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةْ
You will have, love of authority and you will regret it on the Day of Judgment.
It will be regret on the Day of Judgment.
So, we need to be careful brothers and sisters, we need to be very careful.
Whom did Rasool Allah ﷺ then give Rayi'ah(راية), whom did he give, the banner to?
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Where is Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)?
They told him;
اِنَّهُ اَرْمَدْ يَا رَسُول الله
They told him that he's suffering the disease in his eyes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Bring him, so they brought him, his eyes were shut,
so they had to hold him by the hand and bring him to the Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ put some of this saliva in the eyes of Allah Bin Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) and they were immediately cured.
This is one of the miracles of Rasool Allah ﷺ, one of the many miracles of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and then Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was handed the banner and he told Rasool Allah ﷺ.
اُقَاتِلُهُمْ يَا رَسُوْلْ الله حَتَّى يَكُوْنُوْا مِثْلَنَا
Should I fight them until, they become like us.
And this is interesting Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) didn't say Should I fight them, until they become Muslim.
What did he say?
He said: Should, I fight them until they become like us.
So, they were the living example of Islam, they and Islam were synonymous.
So, whether he said, shall I fight them until they become Muslim
or shall I fight them until they become like us, doesn't make a difference,
they mean the same thing.
something that we cannot say today, something we cannot claim today.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اِنْفِذ عَلَى رِسْلِكْ
حَتَّى تَنْزِلَ بِسَاحَتِهِمْ ثُمَّ ادْعُهُمْ اِلَىْ الْاِسْلَامْ
ووَاَخْبِرْهُمْ بِمَا يَجِبُ عَلَيْهِمْ مِنْ حَقِّ الله تَعَالى
من حَقِّ الله تَعَالى فِيْه، فَوَلله لَا اَنْ يَّهْدِيَ الله بِكَ رَجُلًا وَاحِدَا خَيْرُ الَّكَ مِنْ خُمْرً نَّعْمْ
In Bukhari(بخاريْ) Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
Go to them, until you reach
بِسَاحَتهِمْ
the area in front of them, and then invite them to Islam
and inform them about their duties towards Allah
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
In the name of Allah, if Allah guides through you , one man, it's better for you than, the best of camels.
Here is an example of Ghaneemah(غنيمة) and guidance
if Allah guides one man through you, it's better for you than Ghaneemah(غنيمة)
it's better for you than the greatest Ghaneemah(غنيمة).
And this, points out to us the purpose of Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
The paramount, the most important goal of Jihad(جهاد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
is to spread the truth, it is to invite others to Islam, it is to save them from hellfire, it is to benefit them
with the greatest benefit, it is to provide them with the best thing and, that is Islam.
And this is, what makes war in a Islam completely different, than any other type of war
any other war, that happens in the world.
Other wars are fought for booty, they are fought for hunger, for power,
they are fought for revenge, they are fought for different reasons.
But here we see the noble, idea of fighting, in order to save people
and that's why Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
I am amazed, by people who are dragged into paradise in chains.
Meaning people sometimes, are forced into Jannah(جنة) against their will.
And this because, they were fought and then they became Muslim
and Rasool Allah ﷺ, is turning the attention of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
that you should first, give them Da'wah(دعوة), before fighting them.
And that if one man becomes Muslim, that's better for you than the best of Ghaneemah(غنيمة).
The slogan of the Muslims in that battle
they used to have different slogans in different battles, in this particular battle, it was;
يَامَنْصُوْرَ أَمِتْ أَمِتْ
O, Victor, kill, kill or put to death, put to death.
And this is something that they would repeat.
Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ) says that Salamah(سلمة) narrated
that Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) carried the banner and walked to them with confidence
and we are following him until, he reached next to their fortress
and posted the banner, in a pile of rocks, under the fortress.
So, a Jew looked to Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب), from on top of the fortress
he looked down at Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) from top of the fortress and said;
Who are you?
قَالَ  اَنَا عَلِيْ بن ابي طالب
I am Ali(علي), the son of Abu Talib(ابو طالب).
The Jew said;
تعَالَيْتُمْ وَمَا اُنزِلَ على مُوسى
You will rise in the name of, what has been revealed on Musa(موسى).
Because the name of Ali(علي),
Ali(علي) is from Al'luww(عَلُوّْ) and that is something that is high and exalted.
So, when this Yahoodi(يهودي) heard the name of Ali(علي) he said, that you will rise.
He took it as a bad omen because of the name of Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب)
it means Al'luww(عَلُوّْ) and it could mean overcoming, it could mean exalted, it could mean high,
so all of the meanings are meanings, that were bad omen, to this Yahoodi(يهودي).
فَمَا رَجَعَ حَتَّى فَتَحَ الله عَلَيْهْ
By the time, he returned Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) has opened that fortress.
As Rasool Allah ﷺ has promised.
Some spotlights from the Battle of Khaybar(خيبر), examples of Sahabah رضي الله عنهم and other examples too.
Examples of good and bad
there was this man, who was doing a very good job in fighting, the enemies of Allah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ pointed towards him and said, He is one of the people of hellfire.
And this was kind of shocking, to the Sahabah(صحابه) because of the strength of this man,
and the good work that he was doing.
It say, in one narration;
حَتَّى كَادَ بَعْضهُمْ اَنْ يَرْتَابْ
Some of them were going to have doubts
because on one hand, Rasool Allah ﷺ says that he is from the people of hellfire.
And one hand they see a Mujahid(مجاهد) Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) who is fighting.
Atleast that's what, they see because, they don't know what's in the heart of this man.
But they see that, he's very strong fighter,
and these Sahabah(صحابه), they understood the Faza'el(فضائل), the virtues of fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله)
so they saw it, something very striking, and strange, ironic.
So, one of them said: "I'm going to follow this man and see what happens."
So, he speeds up, he would speed after him.
If he slow down, he slow down after him.
I mean, he's, he's trailing him, following him, wherever he goes.
And then the man was injured, it was painful
and the man did not have Sabr(صبر), did not have patience.
So, he took an arrow from his quiver and he slit his throat.
The Sahabah(صحابه), who saw that, went rushing to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
O Rasool Ullah what you said, became true.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُمْ يَا فُلَانْ فَاَذَّنْ اَنَّه’ لَا يَدْخُلُ الْجَنَّةْ اِلَّا مُؤمِنْ وَاَنَّ اللهَ يُؤيدُ هَذَ الدِّيْنْ بِرَجُل فَاجِرْ
Go and announce to everyone, that only a believer will enter into paradise.
And that Allah could support this religion, through a corrupt person.
This was a corrupt person who's deeds gave support to Islam because, he was a good fighter.
So, definitely what he did, was supportive of Islam, even though he was a corrupt person.
So, not everyone that is supporting the religion, is a believer,
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying announce to the people, and let them know
that only the believer will enter into Jannah(جنة).
So, not everybody whom you think, whom you see, as being good is a person that would go to Jannah(جنة).
This doesn't mean that we should start doubting the intentions of people.
No, that's not what is meant by this.
But we cannot make a judgment for certain that such and, such person is in Jannah(جنة),
that's something that, we do not know.
That is something that only Allahعَزّوجَلّ knows
and we cannot judge and make a definite opinion
that particular person is entering into Jannah(جنة)
except if Rasool Allah ﷺ has given us that Shahadah(شهادة)
such as the Shahadah(شهادة), he gave to the 10
and the Shahadah(شهادة) that he gave to Bilal رضي الله عنه
and the Shahadah(شهادة) that he gave to Abdullah Ibn Salam(عبدالله إبن سلام)
and the Shahadah(شهادة) that he gave, some other Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
The next example there was a Bedouin, A'araabi(اعرابي) he became Muslim
and then he went out with Rasool Allah ﷺ in the Battle of Khaybar(خيبر)
the Muslims won in the Battle of Khaybar(خيبر) and it was a great booty.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ divided the booty among the Sahabah(صحابه)
and after a long period of poverty now, they have something to live on.
One of the best Ghanaem(غنائم) that, they ever had was the Ghaneemah(غنيمة) of Khaybar(خيبر).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ, told some Sahabah(صحابه) to take this and give it to the Bedouin.
This is his share of the Ghaneemah(غنيمة), so his share was brought him.
He said:
مَا هَذَا
What is this?
They said: This is your share of the booty.
He went back to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said;
مَا هَذَا
What is this?
He was told, this was Ghaneemah(غنيمة) this is your share.
He said;
مَا عَلَى هَذَا تَّبَعْتُكْ
This is not why, I became Muslim and followed you.
اِنَّمَا اتَّبَعْتُكَ عَلَى أن أرمى هَاهُنَا بِسَهْمٍ فَاَدْخُلُ الْجَنَّة، فَاُقْتَل فَاَدْخُلَ الْجَنَّة
This is not why, I followed you.
I followed you, so that I would be hit right here
and he pointed to his neck with an arrow and then I would be killed
and I would enter into paradise.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله)
look at the purity of his Fitrah(فطرة), Ghaneemah(غنيمة) is Halal(حلال) for him.
I mean, it is in fact, the best of Rizq(رزق)
because Allahعَزّوجَلّ has made Ghaneemah(غنيمة) the Rizq(رزق) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was a shepherd before Prophet hood,
and he was a businessman, before Prophet hood
but after Nabuwwa(نبوة), his Rizq(رزق) came from the booties of war.
He stopped working, he discontinued, his former professions and gave his time, full time,
to spreading the Da'wah(دعوة) of Allah.
So, how did he survived.
He survived through, his share of Al-Ghaneemah(ألغنيمه).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in the Hadith(حديث).
بُعِثْتُ بِالسّيْفْ، بَيْنَ يَدَيِّ السَّاعَةْ، وَجُعِلَ رِزْقِي، تَحْتَ ظِلْ رُمْحِيْ
I was sent with the sword, before the hour
and my sustenance comes from under the shade, of my spear.
So, if Allahعَزّوجَلّ has made it, the Rizq(رزق) of Rasool Ullah
it is the best form, of sustenance according to the opinion of Ulema(علماء)
such as Ibn Rajab Al-Hanbali(إبن رجب ألحنبلي), when he commented on this Hadith(حديث).
So, it is the best form of Rizq(رزق) and this Bedouin said: I don't want it.
Something that all of the Sahabah(صحابه) are accepting and he voluntarily said: I don't want this.
So, this is a man, who's not looking for the bottom line
this is a man whose heart has absorbed Islam
and he has reached to the level where he's only thinking about Jannah(جنة), he's only thinking about meeting Allah.
and he is a Bedouin, simple man, who doesn't have a lot of knowledge
but his Fitrah(فطرة) was clean he told Rasool Allah ﷺ.
مَا عَلَى هَذَا اتَّبَعْتُكْ
I did not followed you for this?
I followed you, so said that, I would be struck with an arrow right here, and enter into Jannah(جنة)
and then in another battle, Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) well let's go back and see what Rasool Ullah said;
When he made that statement, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him.
اِنْ تَصدق الله يَصدق
If you are true with Allah, Allah will fulfill what you want.
Allah will be true with you.
Meaning Allah will give you, what you desire?.
And Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), we find that all over in Qur'an and Hadith(حديث).
وَالَّذِينَ اهْتَدَوْا زَادَهُمْ هُدًى
The ones, who seek guidance, Allah will give it to them,
وَالَّذِينَ جَاهَدُوا فِينَا لَنَهْدِيَنَّهُمْ سُبُلَنَا ۚ
And the ones who struggle in Our path we will guide them to Our path.
So,
مَنْ تَقَرَّبَ إليَّ شِبْرًا تَقَرَّبْتُ إِلَيْهِ ذِرَاعًا، اِن مشيت إليَّ هَرْوَلَت إليَّك
If you walk towards Allah, Allah will run towards you.
So, it depends on your efforts.
If you are truthful, with Allah, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, Allah will be true with you.
And this man you can see in his statement, truth.
You can see honesty, you can see the willingness to sacrifice.
In another battle he was hit with an arrow in the exact place, where he pointed his finger towards.
So, he was brought to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Is it him.?
They said: Yes it is him.
What did Rasool Allah ﷺ do?
Rasool Allah ﷺ put his own garment over him, to be put with him in his grave.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) the garment, that has touched the skin of Rasool Allah ﷺ
you know we talked about, the Sahabah(صحابه) would fight over the hair of Rasool Ullah
and they would fight over, the droplets of Wadhoo(وضوء) that would fall from, his body
so that they would rub it over their selves.
They would fight, to get that blessing from Rasool Ullah,
and this Bedouin is getting it, without any effort.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is wrapping him, in his own Garment.
The garment that has touched, the skin of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ put him in his grave and he made for him, a long Dua(دُعَا),
the narrator of this Hadith(حديث), and this Hadith(حديث) is authentic, and it is in Al-Bayhaqi(البيهقي)
The narrator of this, he said;
The part that I remembered, or the part that I heard, from the Dua(دُعَا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ was;
اَللَّهُمَّ هَذَا عَبْدُكَ خَرَجَ مُجَاهِدًا فِيْ سَبِيْلِكْ قُتِلَ شَهِيْدًا وَ اَنَا عَلَى ذَالِكَ شَهِيْدْ
O Allah! This is Your servant, he came forth, Mujahid(مجاهد),
struggling, in Your path, and he was killed as a Shaheed(شهيد) and I am a witness of that,
Allah-Ho-Akbar(الله اكبر), Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله),
Rasool Allah ﷺ is saying I'm a witness that, this man is Mujahid(مجاهد) and he is a Shaheed(شهيد).
What a better witness, what a great badge of honor,
that was given to this simple Bedouin, with little knowledge
but because of his Sidq(صدق), because of his truth, he was rewarded this great reward.
The next example Abu'l Yussr(أبولْيُسْر), a companion of Rasool Allah ﷺ, he said;
اِنِّيْ لَمع رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بِخَيْبَرْ
I was with Rasool Allah ﷺ in Khaybar(خيبر), one day.
اِذْ اَقْبَلَتْ غَنَمْ لِرَجُلِ مِنْ اليَهُوْدْ تُرِيْدُ حصنَهُمْ
When we saw sheep belonging to one of the Yahood(يهود)
and the sheep were entering into their fortress.
And we were besieging that fortress.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ saw this sheep and the Muslims apparently were hungry.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَنْ الرَجُلْ يُطْعِمُنَا مِنْ هَذِهِ الْغَنَمْ
Who will feed us from these sheep, Abu'l Yussr(أبولْيُسْر) said: Me, O Messenger of Allah!
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: then go ahead.
قَاَلَ فَخَرَجْتُ اَشْتَدْ مِثْلَ الظَلِيْمْ
I set out running like an ostrich.
Now, Al-Zaleem(ألظليم) is the name that, the Arabs give to the male ostrich.
The ostrich used to live in the Arabian Peninsula.
It was indigenous to the Arabian peninsula but now it became extinct Allah-Ho-Alam(الله اعلم), when
but we don't hear from any of our forefathers that they have seen any ostriches.
So, my it must have been a while, since they ran extinct.
But there's a lot of poetry and stories from old Arabia that talk about the ostrich.
They used to eat, the eggs of the ostrich
and also, they used to feed on, its flesh and it's Halal(حلال)
and they also used the feathers of ostrich were very expensive and
fighters, the knights used to decorate their armor with feathers of the ostrich
and you might have heard that Hamza Bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه in the battle of Uhud(أحَد) had an ostrich feather,
also in Badr(بدر) he had an ostrich feather on his chest, decorating his chest.
And the ostrich is very fast.
They say that the speed of an ostrich could reach to between 65 kilometers per hour to eighty kilometers per hour, it's pretty fast.
So, this Sahabi(صحابي), he said: I set out running like an ostrich, meaning that he was very fast.
فَلَمَّا نَظَرَ اِلَيَّ رَسُوْل الله صلى الله عليه وسلم موَلِّيَّا، قَالَ اَللَّهُمَّ اَمْتِعْنَا بِهْ
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ saw me running, he said: O Allah! Let us enjoy his company.
قَالَ فَاَدركْتُ الْغَنَمْ
So, I reached to the sheep, when the first of them have already entered the fortress.
So he, only was able to catch the last of them.
فَاَخَذْتُ شَائتَيْـنْ مِنْ اُخْرَهَاَ
So, he took two of them,
فَاخْتَزَمْتُهَا تَحْتَ يَدَيْ
So, I hug them, under my arms,
ثُمَّ جِئْتْ بِهِمَا اَشْتَدْ كَاَنَّ هُوْلَيْسَ مَعِيْ شَيْء
And I came back running, as if I was carrying nothing with me.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) running, while he's holding two of these sheep, he said;
I was so light in my running as if, I had nothing with me.
حَتَّى اَلْقَيْتُهُمَاَ  عِنْدَ رَسُوْل الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
Until I dropped them, under the feet of Rasool Ullah.
فَذَبَحوْهُمَا فَاَكَلُوْهُمَا
They slaughtered them and they had a feast.
فَكَانَ اَبُو الْيُسْرْ مَنْ آخِرِ اَصَحَابِ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مَوْتَا
Abu'l Yussr(أبولْيُسْر) was one of the last of the Sahabah(صحابه) to die. Why?
because of the Dua(دُعَا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah said: O Allah, let us enjoy his company.
Abu'l Yussr(أبو الْيُسْر) when he would mentioned this Hadith(حديث), he would cry, he would say;
أمتعوا بي لعمري حتى كنت آخرهم موتا
They enjoyed my company until, I became the last of them, one of the last of them to die.
He was kind of sad that he was, the one left behind
while all of his friends and Rasool Allah ﷺ have passed away before him.
Then we have the incident that occurred with Abdullah Bin Mughaffal رضي الله عنه, one of the companions.
When they opened one of the fortresses in Khyber(خيبر), they found dried fat.
Fat of animals, they would cut it into pieces, and they would dry it in the sun, for future use.
So, there was a sack filled with this dried fat
and Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل) grabbed it and he put it on his shoulder.
He started walking with it towards his company to feed on it.
So, they must have been quite hungry and without sufficient food.
Now, the man responsible for dividing the booty
he saw Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل) walking away with this sack
he walked up to him, and he held the sack from one end.
And he tried to pull it away and saying give it to me, so that it be split among the Muslims.
I mean, according to the laws of, the laws and regulations of dividing, the booty.
Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل), refused.
So, they were pulling Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل) is pulling from one end
and this other companion is pulling from the other end, it's tugging between them
and Rasool Allah ﷺ saw this and smiled
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ, told the man responsible for the Ghaneemah(غنيمة)
just let him go, Leave, Leave it, let him take it.
لَا اَذَالَكْ
Just let him, have it.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was laughing at Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل).
Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل) said: I was quite embarrassed by that
and having this incident happened in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ it's quite embarrassing
but he said I took it away, and I went to my companions and we ate it all.
The scholars derived from this, a Hukum(حكم) that
you're allowed to eat from Ghaneemah(غنيمة) food on the spot
but not take anything with you back,
gold, silver, weapons all that other valuables need to be put with Al-Ghaneemah(الغنيمة) clothes and they need to be split
and the punishment for taking from Al-Ghaneemah(الغنيمة) is very severe.
however Rasool Allah ﷺ allowed Abdullah Bin Mughaffal(عبدالله بن مُغَفَّل) to have this
because as the scholars have derive the Hukum(حكم) that food is exception.
You were allowed to eat, but not take anything with you, all you can eat just like a buffet
all you can eat but you're not allowed to take anything out of the restaurant.
And then we have the Al-Mar'a Al-Ghafariyyah(ألمَرْأةِ الْغَفاريه).
And this story is mentioned Ibn Is'haqq(اِبْنِ اِسْحَاقْ), she's mentioning her story.
She said: I came to Rasool Allah ﷺ along with some women from Ghaffar(غفار).
Ghaffar(غفار) were Bedouins, who were close to Madina
and they were famous for stealing pilgrims, that was their reputation in Arabia before Islam.
They would attack the pilgrims and rob them.
Many of them became Muslim and eventually all of them became Muslim
because of the Barakah(بركة) of the Da'wah(دعوة) of Abu Dhar Al-Ghaffari رضي الله عنه.
So a tribe was such a bad reputation, nevertheless, Allahعَزّوجَلّ guided them. So,
الله يَهْدِيْ مَنْ يَشَآء
Allah guides whomever, He wills.
This woman came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and she came with some other women from Ghaffar(غفار)
and she told Rasool Allah ﷺ, we want to go forth with you
in order that we can take care of the wounded and attend to the other needs of the Muslims.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told her;
عَلَى بَرَكَة االله
Go with the blessing of Allah.
He allowed her to, accompany him
and Rasool Allah ﷺ not only allowed them to accompany the army
but Rasool Allah ﷺ had this young girl, ride on the same camel with him.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ was sitting on Rahal(رحل), the seat
and then behind him, was the luggage and he had her sit on top of the luggage
She was a young girl then, now they arrived, their destination and the camel sat down
and this girl came down from the camel, to see that on the luggage was some blood of hers.
So, she sat curled, she curled herself next to the camel and she was, so embarrassed.
This was her first period, she was quite embarrassed by what happened
because of the blood on the luggage of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and she just sat there next to the camel doing nothing.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ saw that she was upset and then he also saw the blood on the luggage.
So he said;
مَا لَكِ لَعَلَّكِ نَفِسْت
What's wrong with you, have you had, your period?
She said: Yes,
Rasool Allah ﷺ told her: Clean yourself
and take a vessel of water and put some salt in it.
And then wipe out the blood from the baggage
so use water with salt, clean the blood from the luggage.
So, she said: She did that.
And then we participated with Rasool Allah ﷺ in the battle.
And when the booty was divided.
Now, the Ulema(علماء) say that women and children are not given a share of the booty
even if they join in fighting.
But the Ameer(أمير) of the army can give them, what's called Radha(رضى)
he can give them something but it's not equal to the share.
He can give them what he sees appropriate but there are not counted as exact shares.
So, she said Rasool Allah ﷺ called me and he had the necklace with him.
And he gave me the necklace and said: This is yours.
And she said: He with his own hands, put it around my neck.
Now, after that, she said: Whenever I would have menstrual period
I would always wash myself with water and salt.
And in fact, in her will she asked that she should be washed with water and salt.
And she said: In the name of Allah, In the name of Allah,
I will never apart with this necklace that was put around my neck by the own hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and when she died, the necklace was left on her neck.
I'm going to leave this story as it is without tampering with it, with my own comments.
I think it's beautiful enough to leave as it is
for you to drive the amazing examples of companionship and love that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had for Rasool Allah ﷺ
and I means Rasool Allah ﷺ did not tell her to permanently use salt for cleansing,
she did that out of love of Rasool Allah ﷺ, she did that to remember Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Ullah did not tell her to wash herself when she dies with water and salt
but she did that because of the memories of Rasool Allah ﷺ that she had
and the whole story of Rasool Allah ﷺ calling her and allowing her to ride with him on a same mount,
she was a young girl and the fact that she offered her help and she's at that young age and she's a Bedouin woman
the love that they had for Islam, the love that they had for Rasool Allah ﷺ
the willingness to sacrifice, the willingness to help.
Where are these meanings now, we have lost a lot of these meanings
and, the embarrassment that she had when she would have her first period
because she messed up with the luggage of Rasool Allah ﷺ, so she was so ashamed of that
and the kindness of Rasool Allah ﷺ and the instructions that he gave her
and then the fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ would call her, after that and remember her
and she is just a member of this large army following Rasool Allah ﷺ.
He calls this girl by name
and he has a necklace and he puts it around her neck with his own hands
the gratitude that Rasool Allah ﷺ had for his companions
and the love and attention that he gave them
all of these are wonderful and amazing examples.
I think there's a lot to learn from the story if we would contemplate and think about it
and that's how we should deal with the Seerah(سيرة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
we should not just listen to the stories to entertain ourselves
we should learn the lessons from them.
Then we have the story of the two Jewish women.
The first is the Zainab Bint Al-Haris(زينب بنت حارث)
this woman belongs to the nobility of Al-Yahood(أليهود)
after the Battle of Khaybar(خيبر) and the defeat Al-Yahood(أليهود)
she held an invitation Waleema(وليمه).
She hosted Rasool Allah ﷺ and some of the Sahabah(صحابه) and she roasted for them a sheep
and, she filled it, with poison and she asked about the particular parts
that Rasool Allah ﷺ loves and she added, the poison in those pieces
Rasool Allah ﷺ accepted the Da'wah(دعوة),
he accepted the invitation and he came with the Sahabah(صحابه)
and she offered them, their meal and they started eating.
Bishr Bin Al-Bara'a(بشر بن البراء), he was the first to swallow a bite from this meat.
Rasool Allah ﷺ had the meat in his mouth but he's didn't swallow it yet.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ dropped it and he said: This bone is telling me that it's poisoned
and then he called the woman and asked her and he said;
Did you poison this for me? She said: Yes.
He said: Why did he do so?
She said: If you're a king then you would be killed and we would be at rest
because we have ridden ourselves from you
but if you were a Prophets Allah will tell you and you would know about it
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told her;
مَا كَانَ الله لِيسلطك عَلَيْهْ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى would not give you the ability to overcome me, or to kill me
and Rasool Allah ﷺ forgave her.
The Sahabah(صحابه) said: Should we kill her, he said: No, leave her.
But then Bishr Bin Al-Bara'a(بشر بن البراء) died because of the mouthful what he had
so, it shows you that this was powerful poison.
So in some narrations it says that Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that she be executed.
Rasool Allah ﷺ survived for three years after that
and in his final days, when he was suffering from fever
and this Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ). Ayesha رضي الله عنها said;
كَانَ النَّبِيُّ صلى الله عليه وسلم يَقُوْلُ فِيْ مَرْضِهِ الَّذِيْ مَاتَ فِيْهِ
يا عائشه: مَا اَزال اَجد اَلَمَ الطَّعَامِ الَّذِي اَكَلتُ بِخَيْبَر
فهذا أوان وجدت انقطاع أبهرى من ذلك السم
Ayesha رضي الله عنها said: Rasool Allah ﷺ would say;
In his final days in the disease that he died because of.
O Ayesha(عائشه), I still find the taste of the food that I ate in khaybar(خيبر).
This is the time when my Ab'hur(أبحر) would be cut, because of that poison.
Abhurr(أبحر) is an artery, I think it's called in English aorta, believe it's spelled A O R T A
and Rasool Allah ﷺ said: This is the time I feel that my Ab'hur(أبحر) will be cut
because of the poison I had in khaybar(خيبر).
Ibn Hishaam(إبن هشام) says;
فَاِنْ كَانَ الْمُسْلِمُوْنَ لَيَرَوْنْ اَنَّ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم مَاتَ شَهِيْدًا، مَعَ مَا اَكْرَمَه اللهُ مِنَّ النَّبُوَّة
The Muslims see that Rasool Allah ﷺ died as a Shaheed(شهيد) in addition to being a Prophet,
so Allah combined for Rasool Allah ﷺ the status of Prophet hood and the status of Shahadah(شهادة), martyrdom.
Now some might see, this as contradicting, the fact that Allah promised Rasool Allah ﷺ
وَاللَّهُ يَعْصِمُكَ مِنَ النَّاسِ ۗ
Allah will protect you from people,
so some scholars said:
That the Allah did promise Rasool Allah ﷺ that He will protect them from Fitnah(فِتْنَه)
He will protect him from defeat
and He will protect him from being killed before, he fulfills his mission.
And when Ayah(آية) was revealed that Allah has completed your religion for you,
now it was time for Rasool Allah ﷺ, to leave this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and meet his Lord.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ died because of this poison, even though it was three years later,
because as Rasool Allah ﷺ said that
he told the woman that you would not have the ability to overpower me, being the Messenger of Allah,
but the pain and the effect of the poison came three years later
when it was already the appointed time for Rasool Allah ﷺ to pass away.
This is the opinion of some of the Ulema'a(علماء) based on the authentic Ahadith(احاديث),
one of them which I just narrated it, to you from Al-Bukhari(ألبخاري).
The next woman is Safiyyah(صفيه)
and In Sha' Allah(اِنْ شَاءالله) we'll leave that to our next session Be-iznillah(بإذن الله).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمةُ الله وَبَرَكَاتُه’